A Guide to the Papers of Edwin A. Alderman
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library
- Series III: Speeches, Addresses, Articles by Alderman
  - 1902 [March 12] Founder's Day Address "The University and the Community" delivered at Tulane University, incomplete copy (complete copy see F 221, Volumes 41 and 44) (Box-folder 18:15)
  - [1902 October 31] Introduction of Principal Booker T. Washington, Tuskegee Institute (Box-folder 18:16)
  - 1903 April 26 Memorial Address - "J.L.M. Curry" delivered at Richmond, Virginia, under the auspices of the Conference for Education in the South, but also given at Boston later in the year, also in print (Box-folder 18:17)
  - [1903 April 26] Address before the 7 th Conference for Education in the South, Richmond, Virginia, with a letter from W.[J.] Harris, Commissioner of Education, July 21, 1903, about the speech (Box-folder 18:18)
  - 1903 June 11 Report on Progress of the Educational Campaign in Southern Education (print) (Box-folder 18:19)
  - 1903 October 2 Address of E.A. Alderman made at the opening exercises of Tulane University as reported in The Daily Picayune (Box-folder 18:20)
  - 1903 November [11] Talk at Noon Assembly at Tulane University on "Some Tests of an Educated Man" in The Olive and Blue, includes printed material and manuscript drafts (Box-folder 18:21)
  - 1903 December 29 Address - "The Value of Southern Idealism" before the American Historical and American Economic Associations, typescript and print (Box-folder 18:22)
  - 1903 December 31 Annual Report of Edwin A. Alderman District Director Southern Education Board for Louisiana (Box-folder 18:23)
  - 1903 Speech - Founder's Day Address Tulane University (Box-folder 18:24)
  - ca. 1903-1904 Speech drafts and notes concerning "Negro education" (Box-folder 18:25)
  - 1904 Speech concerning the Urban University - Drafts, Notes, and Clippings (Box-folder 18:26)
  - [1904 January?] Notes and clippings for a speech on the race question (Box-folder 18:27)
  - [1904 October ?] Speech for Columbia University Sesquicentennial celebration (Box-folder 18:28)
  - 1905 May Article - "School Men of the Hour" in American Education, including notes and clippings used for the article (Box-folder 18:29)
  - 1905June 28 Address - "Yale and the University of Virginia" delivered at the Yale Alumni Banquet, typescript and print (Box-folder 18:30)
  - 1905 July Response to a Toast "The Future of Our Alma Mater" in the University of Virginia Alumni Bulletin, print (Box-folder 18:31)
  - 1905 Summer Brief Speech to the Summer School of the University of Virginia, manuscript (Box-folder 18:32)
  - 1905 October 19 Acceptance Speech by Alderman at the Dedication of Madison Hall, typescript (Box-folder 19:1)
  - 1905 November 21 Speech - "The Making of a National Spirit" delivered at the 137 th Annual Banquet of the New York Chamber of Commerce, typescript and print (Box-folder 19:2)
  - 1905-1906 Report by Alderman to the Southern Education Board as a member of the Campaign Committee representing Virginia and Louisiana (Box-folder 19:3)
  - 1906 March 23 Charter Day Address "The Spirit of the South" delivered at the University of California, Berkeley, typescript and offprint, with a letter, September 17, 1923, from Alderman's secretary asking if the University of California has a copy of his speech (Box-folder 19:4)
  - 1906 May 4 Address "The Achievement of a Generation" delivered at the Conference for Education in the South, Lexington, Kentucky; printed in the South Atlantic Quarterly, typescript and print (Box-folder 19:5)
  - 1906 November 20 "In Memoriam Charles Duncan McIver," delivered at the Memorial Exercises, Greensboro, North Carolina, typescript and later reprint (Box-folder 19:6)
  - 1906 November 27 Speech - Summary of Alderman's speech delivered before the Virginia Society of St. Louis on the industrial progress of the South (Box-folder 19:7)
  - 1906 December 22 Speech "Sectionalism and Nationality" delivered before the New England Society, New York City at Waldorf-Astoria 101 st Anniversary Celebration, print (Box-folder 19:8)
  - 1906 Term Talks to University of Virginia Students, manuscript notes (Box-folder 19:9)
  - 1907 April 13 Speech and Statistics for Founder's Day, University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 19:10)
  - 1907 June 10 Acceptance Speech by Alderman at the Unveiling of the bronze Homeric group by Sir Moses Ezekiel, printed in the Alumni Bulletin July 1907 (Box-folder 19:11)
  - 1907 June [11-12] Address of President Alderman at Finals (Box-folder 19:12)
  - 1907 June [11-12] Memoranda concerning meetings at Finals (Box-folder 19:13)
  - 1907 [June 19?] Opening Talk at the University of Virginia Summer School, manuscript and clippings used for the talk (Box-folder 19:14)
  - 1907 October Convocation Address "Freedom of the Mind" typescript (Box-folder 19:15)
  - 1907 October 26 Speech "The Growth of Public Education in America" delivered at the Jamestown Exposition and published in the Alumni Bulletin January 1908 (Box-folder 19:16)
  - 1907 Speech concerning the South - Notes and clippings (Box-folder 19:17)
  - 1908 January 16 Speech "Reasons for a College Hour" delivered at the inauguration of College Hour, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 19:18)
  - 1908 Mar 22 Address "The Growing South" delivered before the Civic Forum in Carnegie Hall, New York City, printed pamphlet (Box-folder 19:19)
  - 1908 Apr 13 Founder's Day Address introducing James Bryce in the University of Virginia Alumni Bulletin, printed (Box-folder 19:20)
  - 1908 September 28 Convocation Address, printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 19:21)
  - 1908 December 3 Statement by Letter to Egbert G. Leigh concerning the Memorial Meeting for Joseph Bryan, Richmond, printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 19:22)
  - 1908-1919, n.d. Finals - Miscellaneous Materials Used for preparation (Box-folder 19:23)
  - [1908?] Speech "An Argument for the Creation of a State Geological Survey and its Proper Location" (Box-folder 19:24)
  - [1908?] Prospectus for the Library of Southern Literature with Alderman as Editor in Chief with Joel Chandler Harris (Box-folder 19:25)
  - 1909 Jan 19 Address "Poe and the University" delivered in Cabell Hall, University of Virginia, published in the Alumni Bulletin, April 1909, printed (Box-folder 19:26)
  - 1909 February 4 Open Letter of President E.A. Alderman to Mrs. Norman V. Randolph, President of the Richmond Chapter, United Daughters of the Confederacy, Richmond, Virginia, concerning the Lee Essay Contest (Box-folder 19:27)
  - [1909 February?] Speech concerning the success of the endowment fund drive (Box-folder 19:28)
  - 1909 Apr 13 Founder's Day Statement, published in the Alumni Bulletin, July 1909, printed (Box-folder 19:29)
  - 1909 May 19 Address "Virginia" delivered in response to the toast "Virginia," at the banquet given by the citizens of Petersburg, Virginia, to the President of the United States [William Howard Taft] and Pennsylvania Governor [Edwin Sydney Stuart], typescript and printed pamphlet, including a later printed edition, 1916, by Charles Scribner's Sons, and a news clipping about the book (Box-folder 20:1)
  - 1909 [Oct 6] Address "A Message from Virginia to Massachusetts" delivered at a dinner given at Harvard during the installation of President A.L. Lowell in printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:2)
  - 1910 January Article "The University of Virginia as an Asset of the State" printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:3)
  - [1910 January?] Statement "The Football Problem" published in the Richmond Times Dispatch and Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:4)
  - 1910 [April 13] Speech - Proposed Founder's Day Welcome and Introductions, not held due to the illness of the speakers, typescript (Box-folder 20:5)
  - 1910 Jun 14 Speech for Alumni Dinner, manuscript (Box-folder 20:6)
  - 1910 Jun 15 Speech accepting the statue of Thomas Jefferson by Moses Ezekiel, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, August 1910 (Box-folder 20:7)
  - [1910 Jul 7] Speech "The Higher Education of Virginia Women" by Ormond Stone (Box-folder 20:8)
  - [1910 August] Speeches delivered at the Presentation of a Loving Cup to Alderman by the Faculty, printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:9)
  - 1910 Oct Speech "Religious Ideals of the University," typescript, also printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:10)
  - [1910?] Essay on George Washington for the Library of Southern Literature, Volume 13, pages 5633-5638, printed (Box-folder 20:11)
  - 1911 Feb 22 Speech "The National Spirit" before the Washington Association of New Jersey, printed (Box-folder 20:12)
  - 1911 Apr 29 Speech "A Virginia Democrat" delivered at a reception given by the "Pewter Platter Club of Norfolk, Virginia, in honor of Woodrow Wilson, typescript, printed, and a news clipping (Box-folder 20:13)
  - 1911 May 15 Speech concerning a Co-ordinate College for Women given during University Hour, typescript and news clipping (Box-folder 20:14)
  - 1911 May Speech concerning the establishment of a college for the education of women, by the state of Virginia, preferably a Co-ordinate College located near the University and controlled by it; very similar speech to the one given during University Hour, perhaps for more general occasions (Box-folder 20:15)
  - 1911 Jun 14 Address at the Alumni Luncheon, manuscript (Box-folder 20:16)
  - 1911 Jun Address to the Class of 1911, printed in Alumni Bulletin, October 1911 (Box-folder 20:17)
  - 1911 Oct 29 Memorial Address at Public Service for Edward Morse Shepard at the College of the City of New York, typescript and printed program (Box-folder 20:18)
  - 1911 Nov 3 Speech at the Inauguration of President Thomas Edward Hodges at the University of West Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 20:19)
  - 1911 Address before the Medical Association of Virginia and North Carolina at Newport News, Virginia, typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, January 1918 (Box-folder 20:20)
  - 1912 Feb 22 Speech "The Problem of Democracy" delivered at The University of Pennsylvania, typescript, printed, and news clipping (Box-folder 20:21)
  - 1912 [March 9] Address before the Alumni of Lynchburg, Virginia, explaining the University of Virginia entrance requirements and standards for graduation, according to the suggestion of R.C. Blackford in his letter to Alderman, dated February 19, 1912, and mentioning another future speech of Alderman to the [Lynchburg] Retail Merchants Association, includes notes for speech (Box-folder 20:22)
  - 1912 Apr 13 Founder's Day Speech, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 20:23)
  - 1912 May 16 Speech at the Jacob Tome Institute, Boarding School for Boys, Port Deposit, Maryland, typescript with some manuscript pages (Box-folder 20:24)
  - 1912 May 25 Speech accepting the Archer Christian Memorial Tablet, Christian died of a football injury on November 13 1909, typescript; also printed in the Alumni Bulletin, July 1912 (Box-folder 20:25)
  - 1912 May 29 Speech at Davidson College, typescript (Box-folder 20:26)
  - 1912 Jun 4 Commencement Address at the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, typescript and printed program (Box-folder 20:27)
  - 1912 June, 1915-16 Notes and Drafts for Finals Speeches, typescript and clipping; also printed in Alumni Bulletin (dates taken from printed item and notation on old folder) (Box-folder 20:28)
  - 1912 Jul 2 Statement "Tribute from Alma Mater to Her Son; Woodrow Wilson" published in Richmond Times Dispatch, typescript and news clipping (Box-folder 21:1)
  - 1912 Sep 28 Speech - Opening Convocation of the 88 th Session of the University of Virginia, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin, October 1912 (Box-folder 21:2)
  - 1912 Oct 16 Speech to University of Virginia students delivered at College Hour (Box-folder 21:3)
  - 1912Report of the Virginia Education Commission, Edwin A. Alderman, Chairman, (his copy) (Box-folder 21:4)
  - 1912, n.d. Notes and Drafts of Speeches on the Proposed Women's College, manuscripts and printed (Box-folder 21:5)
  - 1914 [Feb 14] Memorial Speech concerning Alcee Fortier (1856-1914) (Box-folder 21:6)
  - 1914 April 13 Founder's Day Speech sent by Alderman while away at Saranac, New York, and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:7)
  - 1914 October 2 "A War Letter by President Alderman" addressed to Mrs. Schieffelin and published in the Alumni Bulletin, January 1915 (Box-folder 21:8)
  - 1914 November 23 Address "The Causes of the European War," typescript and printed; later published in the Alumni Bulletin January 1917 (Box-folder 21:9)
  - 1914 November 30 Speech given at the Faculty Dinner (Summary), typescript (Box-folder 21:10)
  - 1915 January 15 Speech before the North Carolina Legislature, Raleigh, North Carolina, typescript (Box-folder 21:11)
  - 1915 February 12 Printed Letter from Alderman concerning the purchase of Monticello (Box-folder 21:12)
  - 1915 March 31 Article "The Need of Co-operation between the University and the State, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:13)
  - 1915 April 13 Founder's Day Address and Acceptance Speech at the Unveiling of the bronze statue of a seated Thomas Jefferson by Karl Bitter and given by Charles R. Crane, New York, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin, April 1915 (Box-folder 21:14)
  - 1915 April 21 Address "Education and Public Service" delivered at the inauguration of Dr. Edward K. Graham (1876-1918) as President of the University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:15)
  - 1915 June 16 Speech at Finals, including Alderman's Greeting to the Alumni, typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, and a news clipping about the visit of Governor Henry Carter Stuart (Box-folder 21:16)
  - 1915 Summer Summer School Speech, including a summary of the Montessori System, manuscript and typescript (Box-folder 21:17)
  - 1915 September 30 Convocation Speech printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:18)
  - 1915 October 12 Printed Letter concerning Alderman's Strong Plea for Military Preparedness printed in Alumni Bulletin and in The Richmond News Leader (Box-folder 21:19)
  - 1915 November 9 Speech "Can Democracy Be Organized?" delivered before the State Literary and Historical Association of North Carolina, typescript and printed pamphlet (Box-folder 21:20)
  - 1915 November 26 Memorial Address "Robert Curtis Ogden (1836-1913), Volunteer Statesman," delivered at the Ogden Memorial Meeting, Richmond, Virginia, typescript and printed in Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:21)
  - [1915] Speech concerning "What a President Does" delivered to the University of Virginia Students, typescripts (Box-folder 21:22)
  - 1916 January 1 Speech "President Alderman's New Year Wish to the Student Body for 1916, typescript (Box-folder 21:23)
  - 1916 February 29 Speech at Lynchburg, Virginia, concerning democracy in America and the impact of the Great War, typescript (Box-folder 21:24)
  - 1916 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:25)
  - 1916 May 5 Speech - Greetings to the University of Virginia Alumni in New York City, typescript (Box-folder 21:26)
  - 1916 May 11 Speech delivered at Hampton Institute, Hampton, Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 21:27)
  - 1916 June 14 Finals Speech, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 21:28)
  - 1916 June 16 Speech delivered to the Alumni, typescript (Box-folder 21:29)
  - 1916 October 3 Convocation Address, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:1)
  - 1916 December 4 Speech "What Students Owe to the University" concerning gambling, delivered during College Hour, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:2)
  - 1916 December 21 "A Brief Report from Dr. Alderman, printed in [Alumni Bulletin?] (Box-folder 22:3)
  - 1916 December 25 Christmas Greetings to Alumni, typescript and printed (Box-folder 22:4)
  - 1916 Speech concerning a Co-ordinate College for Women and Related Material, typescript, printed, correspondence, and news clippings; letters are from the Chairman of the Central Committee [of the Virginia Legislature?], December 24, 1915 and Silas C. Mitchell, January 7 and 13, 1916, all to Alderman about the establishment of a woman's college in Virginia (Box-folder 22:5)
  - [1916?] Thoughts on the subject of the Graduate Department of the University to the Faculty (Box-folder 22:6)
  - [1916?] Alumni Address, typescript (Box-folder 22:7)
  - 1917 February 8 Speech delivered before the Virginia Press Association, at the University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 22:8)
  - 1917 Mar 30 Speech delivered at a University Mass Meeting concerning the entry of the United States into World War I and mentioning the death of James McConnell and plans to establish a unit of the Officers' Reserve Training Corps at the University, typescript (Box-folder 22:9)
  - 1917 April 5 Speech "Democracy and Patriotism" delivered on the occasion of the centenary of the First Presbyterian Church, Wilmington, North Carolina, including typescript, manuscript, correspondence (November 1916) inviting Alderman and President Woodrow Wilson to speak, tentative program, clippings concerning religious education, and a news clipping concerning Alderman's speech (Box-folder 22:10)
  - 1917 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript (Box-folder 22:11)
  - 1917 May 15 Speech delivered at the College of Charleston, South Carolina, typescript (Box-folder 22:12)
  - 1917 May Speech from "French Schools in War Time" in French, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:13)
  - 1917 June 1 Finals Speeches, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:14)
  - 1917 June Article "A Message to Students - Alumni - Parents" concerning the impact of the war upon the colleges and universities of the United States; typescript, printed pamphlet, and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:15)
  - 1917 Sep 24 Speech "Farewell to Monticello Guard" typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:16)
  - 1917 Sep 25 Speech Opening Address delivered at the Y.M.C.A., typescript (Box-folder 22:17)
  - 1917 Oct 4 Convocation Address "The War and Education" typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, and a news clipping concerning the speech (Box-folder 22:18)
  - 1917 Oct [5?] Tribute to Dr. Charles William Kent (1860-1917), printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:19)
  - 1917 Nov 8 Speech delivered at the Albemarle Survey Exhibit, in the Armory of Charlottesville, typescript (Box-folder 22:20)
  - 1917 Dec 25 Christmas Greetings to Alumni, typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, and broadside (Box-folder 22:21)
  - 1917 Article "A Note on Civilian Headships" in Report of the Board of Visitors to the United States Naval Academy (Box-folder 22:22)
  - 1917 Article "The Function and Needs of Schools of Education in Universities and Colleges" printed in Publications of the General Education Board Occasional Papers No. 4 and Alumni Bulletin April 1918 (Box-folder 22:23)
  - [1917] Speech beginning "There is but one theme for a public address in these days and that theme is one's country" concerning patriotism (Box-folder 22:24)
  - 1918 Feb 3 Address delivered at John Marshall High School, a later version of "Can Democracy Be Organized?" typescript and news clipping (Box-folder 22:25)
  - 1918 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:26)
  - 1918 Jun 11 Finals Speech, typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin, and a news clipping (Box-folder 22:27)
  - 1918 [October 26] Tribute to Edward Kidder Graham, manuscript (Box-folder 22:28)
  - 1918 [October] Address "The University of Virginia as a Military Camp" to the Officers and Men of the Students Army Training Corps [at Convocation?], typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:29)
  - 1918 Dec 25 Christmas Greetings to the Alumni, typescript, including a print version from the University of Virginia European Bureau (Box-folder 22:30)
  - 1918 Dedication in The Corks and Curls, typescript (Box-folder 22:31)
  - 1919 Apr 12 Founder's Day Address "The University and Reconstruction," typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:32)
  - 1919 April 25 Speech at the Memorial Service for Ambassador Walter Hines Page (1855-1918), typescript (Box-folder 22:33)
  - 19[19] June 30 Answer to Symposium question "If you were a young man today what business would you go into and why?" in The World (Box-folder 22:34)
  - 1919 June Finals Speech, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:35)
  - 1919 October 2 Convocation Address "A Call to Service" and Introduction of Dr. William Lyon Phelps, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 22:36)
  - 1919 November 21 Presentation Address at the Unveiling of the Lewis and Clark Statue, Midway Park, Charlottesville, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin, with a printed program of the Unveiling Exercises (Box-folder 22:37)
  - 1919 Dedication in The Corks and Curls, typescript (Box-folder 22:38)
  - 1919 Introduction to Education and Citizenship and Other Papers by Edward Kidder Graham, offprints (Box-folder 22:39)
  - [1919] Report of Organizing Committee of the National Committee of the United States for the Restoration of the [Library] of the University of Louvain, typescript (Box-folder 22:40)
  - 1920 April 13 Founder's Day Address, typescript, printed in the Alumni Bulletin and in the Supplement to the University of Virginia Alumni News (Box-folder 23:1)
  - 1920 April 16 Address to High School Principals, typescript (Box-folder 23:2)
  - 1920 April 22 Speech before the School of Citizenship, Virginia Women Voters, typescript (Box-folder 23:3)
  - 1920 June 15 Finals Speech, typescript and program for graduating exercises (Box-folder 23:4)
  - 1920 June Finals Speech "A Farewell Message from President Alderman to the Graduating Classes" typescript, print, and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:5)
  - 1920 September 30 Convocation Address, typescript and printed in the Alumni Bulletin (Box-folder 23:6)
  - 1920 November 11 Remarks during College Hour, remembering the conclusion of the Great War and the sixty-eight University of Virginia alumni and students who lost their lives in World War I, typescript (Box-folder 23:7)
  - 1920 November Message printed on the program for the Virginia-North Carolina Football Game at Thanksgiving, typescript (Box-folder 23:8)
  - 1920 December 18 Article "One Man's Secret of Success" from The Independent about David Franklin Houston (print), with letter from a secretary, June 16, 1924, asking for the copy; includes requested materials about Houston's career sent by Alderman's request, listed in a letter, February 19, 1920 (Box-folder 23:9)
  - 1920 December 25 Christmas Greetings to the Alumni, typescript and printed (Box-folder 23:10)
  - 1920 December "The President's Page" in Alumni News, typescript and printed (Box-folder 23:11)
  - [1920?] Memorandum for Alumni Address, typescript (Box-folder 23:12)
  - [ca. 1920] Letter to the Editor of the Richmond News Leader, Douglas S. Freeman, concerning the recommendation of Governor Westmoreland Davis for the Legislature pass legislation to appoint a Commission on Medical Education in Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 23:13)
  - [1921 Jan 6?] Speech on Co-education at the University of Virginia, typescript (Box-folder 23:14)
  - 1921 Jan 14 "The President's Page" in Alumni News, typescript (Box-folder 23:15)
  - 1921 Feb "The President's Page" in Alumni News, typescript (Box-folder 23:16)
  - 1921 May 31-June 3 Program and Invitation for the Centennial Celebration at the University of Virginia, printed (Box-folder 23:17)